Preliminary Guide to the University Committee on ROTC Records, 1970 - 1971 UA.03.02.0017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
University Committee on ROTC records
1970 - 1971
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Committee on ROTC
UA.03.02.0017
4.5 Linear Feet
The University Committee on ROTC was formed in 1970 to formulate recommendations on the future of ROTC at Duke University. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, testimony, reports, printed materials, reports from other institutions, student course evaluations and questionnaires, notes, and other materials. Major subjects include the role of the Naval and Air Force ROTCs on Duke's campus, the Vietnam War, the draft, and intellectual freedom on university campuses. English.
4500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The University Committee on ROTC Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1972 (A72-67), 1973 (A73-159), and 1977.
Historical Note
The University Committee on ROTC was formed in 1970 at the request of Duke President Terry Sanford. The Committee was established to review the status of the ROTC program at Duke, and to determine whether the program should be abolished, modified, or maintained. Some students and others had complained that ROTC did not fit into the curriculum at Duke, that its coursework did not allow students to think critically, and that Duke symbollically supported the war in Vietnam through its sponsorship of ROTC.
The members of the committee were Aubrey W. Naylor, Thomas G. Wilson, David Pace, Chip Rawlings, and A. Kenneth Pye. In May of 1971, the committee recommended that the ROTC program be continued, although modified, and offered a number of recommendations. ROTC is currently still in operation at Duke University.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, minutes, testimony, reports, printed materials, reports from other institutions, student course evaluations and questionnaires, notes, and other materials related to the Committee's investigations during 1970-1971. One of the Committee's major endeavors was a survey of students who were enrolled or had previously been enrolled in ROTC courses. These student evaluations make up approximately half of the collection.
Arrangement note
The materials are organized by accession number.
Related Material
Report of the University Committee on ROTC to President Terry Sanford, May 25, 1971
Duke University Archives
Military education -- United States; Draft; Academic freedom; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; Duke University. University Committee on ROTC; Duke University. Naval Reserve Officers' Training Corps; Duke University. Air Force Reserve Officers' Training Corps
- Accession Number A72-67
  - Records of Committee's Deliberations
    - Minutes, [2 folders] (Box 1)
    - AFROTC (Box 1)
    - NROTC, [2 folders] (Box 1)
  - Correspondence re: ROTC (Box 1)
  - Printed Material, [4 folders] (Box 1)
  - Articles (Box 1)
- Accession Number A73-159
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Some of the materials included in this series are course evaluation forms and testimonies. Although most of the documents do not contain personally identifiable information, some student names are included. Researchers who use this collection must agree to protect the anonymity of these students by completing a "Request to Conduct Research in Personally-Identifiable Student Records" form. Contact the University Archives for further information and instructions.
  - Meeting Announcements (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
  - ROTC Hearing (Box 1)
  - ROTC Issues and Arguments (Box 1)
  - ROTC Testimonies (Box 1)
  - Questions, Questionnaires, and Answers (Barre & Cocowitch) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Evaluations and Comments (Box 1)
  - Report of the University Committee on ROTC to Pres. Terry Sanford, May 17, 1971 (Box 1)
  - ROTC Report (Box 1)
  - Report of the University Committee on ROTC (Box 1)
  - Text of Report on ROTC to President, May 1971 (Box 1)
  - Report of the University Committee on ROTC (2nd Draft) (Box 1)
  - Comments on the Report of the University Committee on ROTC (Box 1)
  - Report of the University Committee on ROTC (Box 1)
  - ROTC Committee - Loose papers, [2 folders] (Box 2)
  - Student Course Evaluation Questionnaires (Box 2)
  - ROTC Student Program Evaluation
    - Air Force (Box 2)
    - Navy (Box 2)
    - Class of 1971 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1972 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1973 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1974 (Box 2)
  - Student Course and Programs, Forms not included in Summary Statistics (Box 2)
  - ROTC Student Course Evaluation
    - National Science Introductory Courses, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 1, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 2, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 2, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 101, 203, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 51-52, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 51, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 51-52, 101-102, 205, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Air Science 51-52, 101-102, 205, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Naval Science 101, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 101, 401, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 101-102, 301-302, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 201, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 101, undated, [2 folders] (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 101-102, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 102, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 301, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 301-302, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 401 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 401-402, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 102, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Naval Science 101-102, 201-202, 301-302, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Additional Course and Program Evaluations
    - Navy ROTC Completed (Box 3)
    - Air Force ROTC Completed (Box 3)
- 1977 Addition
  - [Clippings, Reports, Correspondence, Minutes, Bulletins, and other materials], [2 folders] (Box 3)